Finding Aid for Mental Health Research Institute (University of Michigan) Records, 1955-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mental Health Research Institute (University of Michigan) records
1955-1995
University of Michigan. Mental Health Research Institute.
9676 Bimu 2
Interdisciplinary unit established in 1955 to conduct a program of basic research in mental health and the behavioral sciences. Administrative files, committee records, and correspondence of directors James Miller, Gardner Quarton, and Bernard Agranoff, and photographs and films.
7.5 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
2 film reels
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Mental Health Research Institute (donor no. 3625. ) in September 1996.
The record group is open to research.
The Mental Health Research Institute (MHRI) is an interdisciplinary unit affiliated with the Department of Psychiatry of the University of Michigan Medical School. Established through the Michigan state legislature in 1955, the Institute was developed by a group of former University of Chicago scientists under the leadership of Dr. James C. Miller. The purpose of the Institute is to conduct an interdisciplinary program of basic research in mental health and the behavioral sciences. The Institute also has a teaching function, offering seminars and laboratory experience to medical and graduate students, psychiatry residents, and postdoctoral scholars.
The Mental Health Research Institute was first housed in offices of the Out-Patient Unit of the Department of Psychiatry. In 1956 the offices were then moved to the sixth floor of the Children's Psychiatric Hospital and later to 1137 East Ann Street, with laboratory facilities in the basement of the Kresge Medical Research Building. In 1960 the new Mental Health Research Institute building was dedicated at the corner of Ann Street and South Forest Avenue.
The directors of the Mental Health Research Institute have been: James G. Miller (1955-1967), Gardner C. Quarton (1968-1983), Bernard W. Agranoff (1983-1995), and co-directors Huda Akil and Stanley J. Watson (1995- ).
For more information about the Mental Health Research Institute, refer to the histories in Box 1 and the Annual Reports in the separate PRINTED MATERIALS subgroup.
The record group is divided into 6 series: History/Background, Administrative Files, Committees, Directors Files, Personnel Files, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Mental Health Research Institute.; Mental health.; Psychology.; Agranoff, Bernard W., 1926-; Quarton, Gardner C.; Miller, James Grier.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agranoff, Bernard W., 1926-; Akil, H. Huda.; Gerard, R. W. (Ralph Waldo), 1900-1974; Mental health.; Miller, James Grier.; Psychology.; University of Michigan. Mental Health Research Institute.; Videotapes.; Waggoner, Raymond W. (Raymond Walter), 1901-
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- History/Background
  The History/Background materials (1956-1977, .25 linear foot) include histories of the institute, information regarding various research projects, compiled records from the first ten years (including correspondence, memos, and meeting minutes), and records on the organizational structure of the institute. Newspaper articles about the Mental Health Research Institute from 1955, 1956, and 1961 are also included, as well as an oversize scrapbook of newspaper clippings from 1965-1977.
  - "First Ten Years" correspondence, memos, minutes, 1956-1966 (Box 1)
  - Histories, 1956-1967 (Box 1)
  - Organizational Structure, 1955-1968 (Box 1)
  - News Articles, 1955; 1956; 1961; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1965-1977 (Volume 1)
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files (1956-1984, 1 linear foot) contain alphabetical subject files dealing with the basic conduct of the business affairs of the institute.
  - Annex, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Appointments and Promotions, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Appropriations, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Behavioral Science Journal, 1956-1973 (Box 1)
  - Budget, 1956-1961 (Box 1)
  - Budget Summary, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Budget Information and Notes, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Budget, General Academic, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Building
    - Architectural and Financial, 1956-1960 (Box 1)
    - Proposal for Second Building Unit, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Clinical Sciences, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Computer System, 1966-1968; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Coordination Areas, General, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Director Search, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Drug Inquiries and Information, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Headly, Peter D. Memorial Fund, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Library Annual Report, 1966-1980 (Box 1)
  - Movie Production, "Prologue to Understanding,", 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Office Supervisor's Manual, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Open House, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Publicity, 1960; 1966; 1969; 1980 (Box 1)
  - Societal Sciences, 1963-1970 (Box 1)
  - Space Allocation, 1964-1978; 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Systems Sciences, 1962-1967 (Box 1)
  - Visiting Scientists, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Visitors, 1965-1970 (Box 1)
- Committees, 1956-1991
  The Committee files (1956-1991, 2 linear feet) contain records of the following MHRI committees: Academic Staff Committee (1956-1970) which became the Senior Staff Committee (1967-1987), Advisory Committee, including the Psychiatry Ad Hoc Committee (1956-1991), Committee of Five, an elected committee of five Senior Staff (1963-1968), Executive Committee (1957-1988), Internal Review Committee (1975-1984), and the Search Committee (1967-1983). These records include meeting agendas, minutes, correspondence, memos, and committee reports.
  - Academic Staff Committee
    - Staff Listings, 1963-1970 (Box 2)
    - Meetings, 1956-1968 (Box 2)
  - Senior Staff Committee
    - Meetings, 1967-1970 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971-1978 (Box 2)
    - Meetings, 1976-1982; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Administrative Minutes, 1979-1982; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Meetings, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee
    - Correspondence, prior to, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1956-1964 (Box 2)
    - Agendas and Minutes, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, Minutes, 10 Year Summary Report, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Minutes, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1972-1983 (Box 2)
    - Psychiatry Ad Hoc Committee, 1974-1983 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, Reports, Agendas, and Minutes, 1980-1991 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Five, 1963-1968 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee
    - Minutes, 1957-1964 (Box 2)
    - Elections, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1971-1983; 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Minutes, Memos, Reports, Vitae, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, Vitae, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
    - Minutes, Appointment Proposals, Memos, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Minutes, Appointments, Vitae, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Internal Review Committee
    - Reports, Correspondence, Memos, Meetings, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1975-1984 (Box 3)
    - Review, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Search Committee
    - Memos, Correspondence, Vitae, and History/Background Information on MHRI, 1967-1983 (Box 3)
- Directors Files, 1960-1995
  The Directors Files (2 linear feet) contain the records of MHRI directors James Miller (1960-1965), Gardner Quarton (1968-1983), and Bernard Agranoff (1963-1995). The Miller and Agranoff files contain only correspondence and memos. The Quarton files consist of a 1974 grant proposal and control files. The control files are bound volumes of outgoing correspondence arranged in chronological order.
  - James G. Miller
    - Miscellaneous Staff Memos, 1960-1963 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence Carbons, 1963-1964; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence Carbons, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Gardner C. Quarton
    - Grant Proposal, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Control Files, 1968-1977; 12 folders (Box 4)
    - Control Files, 1978-1983; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Bernard W. Agranoff
    - Correspondence, 1963-1981 (Box 5)
    - Control Files, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Control Files, 1984-1986; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 5)
- Audio-Visual-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual Materials series includes photographs, 7 video cassettes, and 1 audio cassette. A descriptive index is included in Box 6. There are also two 16 mm oversized film reels, "Prologue to Understanding," a locally produced film about the Mental Health Research Institute, and "Shadows of Stress, Frontiers of Knowledge," a film narrated by MHRI psychologist Stanley Moss. Both have been transferred to VHS tapes.
  - Photographs
    - Photographs, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
    - Photographs, James Miller, undated. (Box 6)
  - Films and Videotapes
    - Video cassettes with index
      - "The Inauguration of the Theophile Raphael Professorship of Neurosciences in Psychiatry,", 1993 (Box 6)
      - "Where Did MHRI Come From and How Did It Begin,", 1994 (Box 6)
      - "Inauguration of the Gardner C. Quarton Professorship of Neurosciences in Psychiatry,", 1993 (Box 6)
      - "A Pharmacological Approach to the Study of the Mind,", 1959 (Box 6)
      - "Inauguration of the Ralph Waldo Gerard Professorship of Neurosciences in the Department of Psychiatry,", 1991 (Box 6)
      - "Prologue to Understanding," c.1967 (Box 6)
      - "Shadows of Stress, Frontiers of Knowledge,", 1962 (Box 6)
    - Film Reels
      - "Prologue to Understanding," c.1967 (16 mm) (Box 6)
      - "Shadows of Stress, Frontiers of Knowledge," (16 mm), 1962 (Box 6)
    - Gardner Quarton Memorial (audio cassette), 1990 (Box 6)
- Mental Health Research Institute Personnel Files
  Personnel Files (1.5 linear feet) include the records of deceased MHRI staff or staff members who are no longer at the institute. These files include correspondence and records regarding hiring and dismissal or retirement, vitae, and research reports. These files are closed and have been moved to Records Center Storage.
  - Carroll, Bernard, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Clay, Margaret (Box 7)
  - Curtis, George, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Davis, Roger E., 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Deutsch, Karl (Box 7)
  - Friedel, Robert (Box 7)
  - Guyer, Melvin J., 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Gyr, John (Box 7)
  - Horvath, William, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Khachaturian, Henry (Box 7)
  - Knesper, David, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Kochen, Manfred, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - McConnell, Jim (Box 8)
  - Platt, John (Box 8)
  - Pollack, Irwin, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Quarton, Gardner, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Radin, Norman, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Reitman, Walter (Box 8)
  - Sellinger, Otto Z., 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Silverman, Albert J. (Box 8)
  - Singer, David, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Tagliacozzo, Renata, 2 folders (Box 8)